Velian Pandeliev

www.velian.ca • vpandeliev@gmail.com • (647) 864 1472

SUMMARY

A versatile professional trained in user experience design with a background in computer science and cognitive psychology, and with four years of experience teaching the fundamentals of human-computer interaction, who has demonstrated an ability to gather rich user insights; convert them into solutions through research, prototyping, and evaluation; and present them to team members, stakeholders, clients, and executives.

SKILLS AND ABILITIES

User Research

- Conducting primary user research through interviews, surveys, and user observation
- Performing secondary user research and statistical analysis of results
- Distilling insights into personas, experience maps, user journeys, job stories, or themes
- Evaluating interfaces through heuristic evaluation and think-aloud usability tests

User Experience Design

- Iterating on design through ideation, wireframes, storyboards, and mockups
- Rapid prototyping using paper, HTML/CSS/JS, InVision, Balsamiq, Bootstrap
- User interface design in Sketch, Illustrator and Photoshop

Technical Skills

- Web development with HTML/CSS/JavaScript, jQuery, React, Django
- Programming experience in Python, Java, JavaScript
- Proficiency in version control, unit testing, productivity software, *nix shell
- Studied and taught object-oriented programming, algorithmic complexity, data structures, and memory management

Interpersonal Skills

- Proven ability to engage with users to identify user pain points, needs, and workflows
- Excellent communication skills demonstrated while interfacing with clients, stakeholders, team members, and executives
- Experience developing and delivering impactful presentations to any targeted audience
- Track record in interdisciplinary collaboration, including in agile/scrum environments
- In-depth experience mentoring and teaching on a wide range of topics and for various skill levels

WORK EXPERIENCE

User Research Moderator

Ubisoft Toronto (2017 - present)

- Designed user testing protocols, surveys, and interview prompts to identify top usability and gameplay issues at various stages of completion for upcoming Ubisoft titles
- Conducted scripted usability think-aloud sessions and naturalistic game appreciation tests for a wide variety of games (e.g., FPS, adventure, racing, flight)
- Performed ongoing gameplay observations, noting confusing and challenging moments
- Synthesized insights and recommendations and delivered these to development teams
- Recruited, guided, and debriefed internal and external participants

Lecturer, Human-Computer Interaction

Department of Computer Science, University of Toronto (2014-present)

- Taught the fundamentals of User Experience including User-Centered Design, research methods, statistics, ideation, prototyping, usability testing, and interface design
- Lectured over 1200 third- and fourth-year computer science students over 6 semesters
- Provided one-on-one mentoring and support to students in independent projects

User Experience Research Intern

Immersive Experiences Lab, HP Inc. (Summer 2016)

- Performed in-depth mixed methods research on 31 Bay Area creative professionals
- Generated rich insights into designer tools and workflows
- Presented results to stakeholders and executives to guide the creation of new products

User Experience Intern

Cloud Platform Business Unit, VMware, Inc. (Summer 2015)

- Performed primary user research and analysis, and synthesized the findings
- Developed a model of the trust relationship between system administrators and decision-supporting dashboards to understand their reluctance to adopt new solutions

Bilingual Alignment and HTML Standards Intern

Communication and Library Services, Statistics Canada (May 2008 - April 2009)

 Collaborated with natural language processing researchers and data scientists to automate page alignment between English and French documents

Simulation Support Technician

Advanced Cognitive Engineering Lab, Carleton University (Summer 2007 - Summer 2008)

- Conducted cognitive psychology research on operator attention and distraction with drivers and helicopter pilots
- Built and prototyped simulations and experimental scenarios

Research Assistant

Centre for Applied Cognitive Research, Carleton University (Summer 2006)

- Programmed lab experiments on mathematical cognition and numeracy
- Conducted lab experiments and debriefing sessions

EDUCATION

Doctoral Research, Computer Science (Human-Computer Interaction)

University of Toronto, Toronto, ON

Withdrawn in good standing (ABD)

- Spearheaded research on interfaces to support the companion activities of responsive reading, i.e., non-linear navigation, superimposed annotation, spatial arrangement
- Completed courses on research methods, serious games, reading comprehension and cognition, and novel interaction techniques
- Supervised a dozen undergraduate projects in areas such as responsive reading, educational technology, and law
- Presented, volunteered, and reviewed submissions for multiple HCI conferences
- Reviewed candidates for the department's M.Sc. in Applied Computing program

M.Sc. Computer Science (Human-Computer Interaction)

University of Toronto, Toronto, ON

Supervisor: Prof. Ronald Baecker

- Developed an online portal to evaluate the effectiveness of mental fitness games on cognitive function in the elderly
- Validated the prototype with six senior users
- Presented results at multiple conferences on serious games, cognitive health, and humancomputer interaction

B.A. Cognitive Science (Cognition & Computation)

Carleton University, Ottawa, ON

Graduated with High Distinction

- Earned an interdisciplinary degree encompassing computer science, artificial intelligence, neuroscience, cognitive psychology, and philosophy of mind
- Successfully completed an Honours project on the effects of visual or auditory distraction on drivers in a state-of-the-art driving simulator
- Awarded the Senate Medal for Outstanding Academic Achievement

REFERENCES

Alexander Thayer, Immersive Experiences Lab, HP Inc. (alexander.thayer@hp.com)

Paul Gries, Department of Computer Science, University of Toronto (pgries@cs.toronto.edu)

Ricardo Jota, Dynamic Graphics Project, University of Toronto (jotacosta@dgp.toronto.edu)